Louis Gruenberg Papers
Louis Gruenberg Papers
1929-1963
Gruenberg, Louis, 1884-1964.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Russian-born composer, pianist. Collection includes manuscript scores, journals, speeches (1934-1939), printed scores, and drawings.
149025
Biographical History
Louis Gruenberg (1884-1964) was a Russian-American composer and pianist.
Born in Russia, Gruenberg was brought to the United States at the age of two. His musical education was in the master class at the Vienna Conservatory in Austria. He began his career as a pianist and made his debut with the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra in 1912; subsequently he appeared in all the major cities of the United States and Europe. He was chairman of the Composition Department of the Chicago Music College from 1931 to 1933, founder of the League of Composers and the Music Guild, a past president of the International Society of Contemporary Music, a charter member of the MacDowell Society, and a member of the Motion Picture Academy of Arts and Sciences.
His awards include prizes from Columbia and RCA Victor Records, the New York Symphony, and the Federation of Musical Clubs (1941), and he was nominated three times for an Academy Award for Best Original Score. He is perhaps best known for the scores of Green Mansions and Emperor Jones (produced by the Metropolitan Opera), but he also composed the music for Jack and the Beanstalk, Helena's Husband, First Symphony, Jazz Suite, Enchanted Isle, and Serenade to a Beauteous Lady. His music for films includes Fight for Life and So Ends Our Night.
Gruenberg was married and had one daughter. Much of his life was spent in Beverly Hill, California.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Louis Gruenberg Papers consist of biographical material (a brief biographical sketch from Who's Who), correspondence (one outgoing letter to the Composers Society of America), manuscripts (journals, radio broadcasts, drawings, and speeches), and published compositions.
Arrangement of the Collection
All material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of composers and musicians; please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Gruenberg, Louis, 1884-1964.; Composers -- United States.; Music -- 20th century.; Musicians -- United States.; Pianists -- United States.; Russian Americans.; Drawings (visual works); Diaries.; Musical scores.; Sheet music.; Speeches (documents); Composers.; Musicians.; Pianists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Who's Who (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Composers Society of America, 1937 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "Conversations with myself", 1930-1950?; journals (Box 1)
  - Drawings, circa 1953 (Box 1)
  - Prayer ("To Mozart in heaven"), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Radio broadcast, CBS "Modern Masters" series, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Serenade, first radio performance of, undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Chicago College of Music, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Composers Society of America, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Dominant Club of Los Angeles, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Hollywood Chamber of Commerce, 1939 (Box 1)
    - MacDowell Society, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Memorial services, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Opera Ball, 1937 (Box 1)
- Published compositions
  - Dance Suite, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Four Diversions, 1930; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - "It's me, oh Lawd", 1933; prayer from Emperor Jones (Box 1)
  - Jack and the Beanstalk, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Viola, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Violina I, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Violina II, 1930 (Box 1)